Guide to the International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 197 Records WAG.154
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 197 Records
Bulk, 1934-1967
1902-1999
WAG.154
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
2.0 linear feet in 2 record cartons and one oversize flat box.
The Stone Derrickmen and Riggers Association, Local 197 of New York, NY was granted its Charter by the International Association of Bridge, Structural, Ornamental and Reinforcing Iron Workers on September 16, 1916. The collection consists of financial and annual reports, publications, correspondence, meeting minutes, contracts and photographs of Local 197. Reproductions of the founding Charter of Local 197 as well as early editions of the Bridgeman and Ironworkers magazine are also included. Approximately forty-five black and white photographs document construction projects throughout New York City from 1902 until the early 1990s.
International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers. Local 197.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Stone Derrickmen and Riggers Association, Local 197 of New York, NY was granted its Charter by the International Association of Bridge, Structural, Ornamental and Reinforcing Iron Workers on September 16, 1916. The International, founded in 1896 by sixteen delegates from across the United States, represents ironworkers laboring on bridges, structural steel, ornamental and architectural metals, and in shops. During the early years of Local 197, the International had frequent jurisdictional disputes with the American Federation of Labor, a factor which contributed to the failure of the 1919 Great Steel Strike which had attempted to reorganize the industry. With the advent of the New Deal, the International entered a period of expansion which continued through the 1950s. Local 197 worked on a variety of historic projects, including the Cathedral of St John the Divine and the "Columbia Triumphant" statue at Columbus Circle. Originally dominated by German, Jewish and Irish craftsmen, the local's membership became more diverse by the 1980s, as a result of court orders regarding affirmative action.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of financial and annual reports, publications, correspondence, meeting minutes, contracts and photographs of the Stone Derrickmen and Riggers Association, Local 197. Reproductions of the founding Charter of Local 197 as well as early editions of the Bridgeman and Ironworkers magazine are included. There are records of the Welfare Funds and Apprenticeship programs of both Local 197 and Stone Setters Local 84, as well as correspondence between the two unions and the Building Trades Employers Association. The collection also includes contracts and agreements between the Local and employers. Approximately forty-five black and white photographs document construction projects throughout New York City from 1902 until the early 1990s. Major projects undertaken by the Local, such as the Cathedral of St John the Divine and the Hanover National Bank, are represented. Also included in the collection is union ephemera such as an insignia, stickers and a large (approximately 13 inch) nail.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Thomas Humphrey, Business Manager of Stone Derrickmen and Riggers, Ironworkers Local 197 in 2000. The accession numbers 1950.158, 2000.026, NPA.2002.019 and NPA.2003.009 are associated with this collection.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Related Archival Materials
Building Trades Employers Association Records (WAG 196)
Building Trades Oral History Project, Audio (OH 045)
International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 0361 Records (WAG 156)
International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 580 Records (WAG 214)
Jack Doyle New York City Construction Photographs (PHOTOS 124)
McNamara Defense Committee Records (TAM 033)
New York Building Congress Records (WAG 167)
Building Trades Employers' Association.; International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers.; Stone Derrickmen and Riggers Association, Local 197.; blueprints (reprographic copies); Clippings files.; Construction industry |z New York (State) |z New York.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Iron and steel workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Labor unions |x Construction workers |z New York (State); Magazines (Periodicals); Minutes.; New York (N.Y.) |x Buildings, structures, etc.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Skyscrapers |x Construction
- Charter - Application - Local 197, 1916 (Box 1)
- History - Bridgeman and Ironworkers Magazine (35 folders), 1916-1950 (Box 1)
- Trial Balances and Reports, 1934 (Box 1)
- Trial Balances and Reports, 1925 (Box 1)
- Trial Balances and Reports, 1923 (Box 1)
- William Angus - Building Trades Employers Association, undated (Box 1)
- William Angus - Miscellaneous (including Blueprints), 1934 (Box 1)
- [Booklets (Stone Setters Welfare Fund, Local 84; National Recovery Administration)], 1934-1961 (Box 1)
- Publications and Correspondence, 1934-1987 (Box 1)
- William Angus - Stone Setters Welfare Fund, 1950 (Box 1)
- [Pension and Welfare Funds], 1964-1967 (Box 1)
- [Annual Reports], 1923-1925 (Box 1)
- Trial Balances and Reports, 1935 (Box 1)
- Local 84 Stone Setters - Apprenticeship Records, 1946-1959 (Box 1)
- Local 84 Stone Setters - Welfare Fund Minutes, 1960 (Box 1)
- Local 84 Stone Setters - Apprenticeship Program, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
- Apprenticeship Agreements, 1924-1925 (Box 1)
- Building Trades Employers Association, 1957-1964 (Box 1)
- Building Trades Employers Association, 1934-1988 (Box 1)
- Trial Balances and Reports, 1924 (Box 1)
- Stone Setters - Welfare, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
- Stone Setters - Contractor's Association, 1918-1978 (Box 1)
- [Agreements], 1923-1990 (Box 2)
- Ron Gallagher, 1979-1990 (Box 2)
- [Clippings, Photographs], 1903-1957 (Box 2)
- Inter Union Correspondence (Local 197, Local 84), 1990, undated (Box 2)
- Cathedral of St John the Divine, 1928-1934 (Box 2)
- Handwork Agreement - Local 84 and Local 197, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
- Work Performed by Derrickmen, 1923-1979 (Box 2)
- St John the Divine, 1925-1952 (Box 2)
- [Agreements], 1933-1973 (Box 2)
- [Agreements and Constitutions], 1913-1963 (Box 2)
- National and Local Stone Setters Association, 1920-1967 (Box 2)
- Stone Setters - Wage Agreements, 1932-1961 (Box 2)
- [William Angus - Blueprints], 1960-1965 (Box 2)
- Derricks, 1921-1948, undated (Box 2)
- Leaflets and Clippings, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
- Agreements and Constitutions, 1919-1990 (Box 2)
- Contracts and Constitutions, 1926-1997 (Box 2)
- [Clippings], 1927-1981 (Box 2)
- [Miscellaneous], undated (Box 2)
- Marriot Hotel (photographs), circa 1992 (Box 2)
- Broadway Central Hotel Collapse (photographs), circa 1966 (Box 2)
- ["Columbia Triumphant", Columbus Circle] (photographs), 1980 (Box 2)
- Trinity Church (photographs), undated (Box 2)
- Trinity Building, Angus Collection (photographs), 1906 (Box 2)
- [Union Officers (Ron Gallagher and John Humphrey)] (photographs), undated (Box 2)
- Union Insignia and Stickers, undated (Box 2)
- Harper's Weekly, 1884 - Statue of Liberty (Reproduction), undated
- Large Nail (artifact), undated (Box 2)
- [Hanover National Bank, 2 Wall St NYC] (24 photographs), 1902 (Box 3)